<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>James PW Robinson on James PW Robinson</title>
    <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in James PW Robinson on James PW Robinson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Maximising sustainable nutrient production from coupled fisheries-aquaculture systems</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/willer2022-ps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/willer2022-ps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-badge-details=&#39;right&#39; data-altmetric-id=&#34;123889310&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aquaculture expansion is expected to meet growing demand for sustainable animal-source foods. Yet marine-fed species already require millions of tonnes of wild-caught fish for feed, over 90% of which are nutritious  food-grade species. Allocating feed fish for human consumption could  reduce pressure on marine resources while increasing seafood production. We examine micronutrient flows (the transfer of micronutrients from  feed to fish) in Scotland’s farmed salmon industry, which is  particularly reliant on marine feeds, to show that 1–49% of essential  dietary minerals and fatty acids available in wild fish are retained in  farmed salmon. Using three alternative production scenarios we show that reducing marine feeds in salmon production and allocating wild-caught  feed fish for human consumption could produce more nutritious seafood  and leave 66–82% of feed fish in the sea. Using global data on  marine-fed aquaculture production, we show that removing wild-caught  fish from salmonid production could leave 3.7 Mt fish in the sea while  increasing global seafood production by 6.1 Mt.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing fisheries for maximum nutrient yield</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-ff/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-ff/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-badge-details=&#39;right&#39; data-altmetric-id=&#34;123231360&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wild-caught fish are a bioavailable source of nutritious food that, if  managed strategically, could enhance diet quality for billions of  people. However, optimising nutrient production from the sea has not  been a priority, hindering development of nutrition-sensitive policies.  With fisheries management increasingly effective at rebuilding stocks  and regulating sustainable fishing, we can now begin to integrate  nutritional outcomes within existing management frameworks. Here, we  develop a conceptual foundation for managing fisheries for multispecies  Maximum Nutrient Yield (mMNY). We empirically test our approach using  size-based models of North Sea and Baltic Sea fisheries and show that  mMNY is predicted by the relative contribution of nutritious species to  total catch and their vulnerability to fishing, leading to trade-offs  between catch and specific nutrients. Simulated nutrient yield curves  suggest that vitamin D, which is deficient in Northern European diets,  was underfished at fishing levels that returned maximum catch weights.  Analysis of global catch data shows there is scope for nutrient yields  from most of the world&amp;rsquo;s marine fisheries to be enhanced through  nutrient-sensitive fisheries management. With nutrient composition data  now widely available, we expect our mMNY framework to motivate  development of nutrient-based reference points in specific contexts,  such as data-limited fisheries. Managing for mMNY alongside policies  that promote access to fish could help close nutrient gaps for coastal  populations, maximising the contribution of wild-caught fish to global  food and nutrition security.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate-induced increases in micronutrient availability for coral reef fisheries</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-oe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-oe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-badge-details=&#39;right&#39; data-altmetric-id=&#34;120363675&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate change is transforming coral reefs, threatening supply of  essential dietary micronutrients from small-scale fisheries to tropical  coastal communities. Yet the nutritional value of reef fisheries and  climate impacts on micronutrient availability remain unclear, hindering  efforts to sustain food and nutrition security. Here, we measure  nutrient content in coral reef fishes in Seychelles and show that reef  fish are important sources of selenium and zinc and contain levels of  calcium, iron, and omega-3 fatty acids comparable with other  animal-source foods. Using experimental fishing, we demonstrate that  iron and zinc are enriched in fishes caught on regime-shifted macroalgal habitats, whereas selenium and omega-3 varied among species. We find  substantial increases in nutrients available to fisheries over two  decades following coral bleaching, particularly for iron and zinc after  macroalgal regime shifts. Our findings indicate that, if managed  sustainably, coral reef fisheries could remain important micronutrient  sources along tropical coastlines despite escalating climate impacts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Secure local aquatic food systems in the face of declining coral reefs</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/hicks2021-oe/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/hicks2021-oe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;   10.1016/j.oneear.2021.08.023&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coral reefs are harbingers of environmental change. In this issue of OneEarth, Eddy et al. analyze long-termdeclines in reef condition and fish catches. Here, we highlight how policies that secure coral reefs as localfood systems can safeguard diverse, nutrient rich diets and support vulnerable social-ecological systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Micronutrient supply from global marine fisheries under climate change and overfishing</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/maire2021-cb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/maire2021-cb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-badge-details=&#39;right&#39; data-altmetric-id=&#34;110037730&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;   10.1016/j.cub.2021.06.067&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fish are rich in bioavailable micronutrients, such as zinc and iron, deficiencies of which are a global food security concern.Global marine fisheries yields are threatened by climate change and overfishing, yet understanding of how these stressors affect the nutrients available from fisheries is lacking. Here, using global assessments of micronutrient content and fisheries catch data, we investigate how the vulnerability status of marine fish species may translate into vulnerability of micronutrient availability at scales of both individual species and entire fishery assemblages for 157 countries. We further quantify the micronutrient evenness of catches to identify countries where interventions can optimize micronutrient supply. Our global analysis, including &amp;gt;800 marine fish species, reveals that, at a species level, micronutrient availability and vulnerability to both climate change and overfishing varies greatly, with tropical species displaying a positive co-tolerance, indicating greater persistence to both stressors at a community level. Global fisheries catches had relatively low nutritional vulnerability to fishing. Catches with higher species richness tend to be nutrient dense and evenly distributed but are more vulnerable to climate change, with 40% of countries displaying high vulnerability. Countries with high prevalence of inadequate micronutrient intake tend to have the most nutrient-dense catches, but these same fisheries are highly vulnerable to climate change,with relatively lower capacity to adapt. Our analysis highlights the need to consolidate fisheries, climate, and food policies to secure the sustainable contribution of fish-derived micronutrients to food and nutrition security.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changing role of coral reef marine reserves in a warming climate</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/graham2020-nc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/graham2020-nc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1038/s41467-020-15863-z&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Coral reef ecosystems are among the first to fundamentally change in structure due to climate change, which leads to questioning of whether decades of knowledge regarding reef management is still applicable. Here we assess ecological responses to no-take marine reserves over two decades, spanning a major climate-driven coral bleaching event. Pre-bleaching reserve responses were consistent with a large literature, with higher coral cover, more species of fish, and greater fish biomass, particularly of upper trophic levels. However, in the 16 years following coral mortality, reserve effects were absent for the reef benthos, and greatly diminished for fish species richness. Positive fish biomass effects persisted, but the groups of fish benefiting from marine reserves profoundly changed, with low trophic level herbivores dominating the responses. These findings highlight that while marine reserves still have important roles on coral reefs in the face of climate change, the species and functional groups they benefit will be substantially altered.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversification insulates fisher catch and revenue in heavily exploited tropical fisheries.</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2020-sa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2020-sa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1126/sciadv.aaz0587&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Declines in commercial landings and increases in fishing fleet power have raised concerns over the continued provisioning of nutritional and economic services by tropical wild fisheries. Yet, because tropical fisheries are often data-poor, mechanisms that might buffer fishers to declines are not understood. This data scarcity undermines fisheries management, making tropical fishing livelihoods particularly vulnerable to changes in marine resources. We use high-resolution fisheries data from Seychelles to understand how fishing strategy (catch diversification) influences catch rates and revenues of individual fishing vessels. We show that average catch weight decreased by 65% over 27 years, with declines in all nine species groups coinciding with increases in fishing effort. However, for individual vessels, catch diversity was associated with larger catches and higher fishing revenues and with slower catch declines from 1990 to 2016. Management strategies should maximize catch diversity in data-poor tropical fisheries to help secure nutritional security while protecting fishing livelihoods.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accounting for the bin structure of data removes bias when fitting size spectra</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/edwards2020-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/edwards2020-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Size spectra are recommended tools for detecting the response of marine communities to fishing or to management measures. A size spectrum succinctly describes how a property, such as abundance or biomass, varies with body size in a community. Required data are often collected in binned form, such as numbers of individuals in 1 cm length bins. Numerous methods have been employed to fit size spectra, but most give biased estimates when tested on simulated data, and none account for the data’s bin structure (breakpoints of bins). Here, we used 8 methods to fit an annual size-spectrum exponent, b, to an example data set (30 yr of the North Sea International Bottom Trawl Survey). The methods gave conflicting conclusions regarding b declining (the size spectrum steepening) through time, and so any resulting advice to ecosystem managers will be highly dependent upon the method used. Using simulated data, we showed that ignoring the bin structure gives biased estimates of b, even for high-resolution data. However, our extended likelihood method, which explicitly accounts for the bin structure, accurately estimated b and its confidence intervals, even for coarsely collected data. We developed a novel visualisation method that accounts for the bin structure and associated uncertainty, provide recommendations concerning different data types and have created an R package (sizeSpectra) to reproduce all results and encourage use of our methods. This work is also relevant to wider applications where a power-law distribution (the underlying distribution for a size spectrum) is fitted to binned data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climatic and local stressor interactions threaten tropical forests and coral reefs</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/franca2020-pt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/franca2020-pt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-badge-details=&#39;right&#39; data-altmetric-id=&#34;120363675&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tropical forests and coral reefs host a disproportionately large share of global biodiversity and provide ecosystem functions and services used by millions of people. Yet, ongoing climate change is leading to an increase in frequency and magnitude of extreme climatic events in the tropics, which, in combination with other local human disturbances, is leading to unprecedented negative ecological consequences for tropical forests and coral reefs. Here, we provide an overview of how and where climate extremes are affecting the most biodiverse ecosystems on Earth and summarize how interactions between global, regional and local stressors are affecting tropical forest and coral reef systems through impacts on biodiversity and ecosystem resilience. We also discuss some key challenges and opportunities to promote mitigation and adaptation to a changing climate at local and global scales.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fishing and habitat control grazing potential across 72 coral reefs</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/post/func-grazing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/post/func-grazing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is my &lt;a href=&#34;https://fesummaries.wordpress.com/2019/09/26/fishing-and-habitat-quality-control-grazing-functions-across-72-coral-reefs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Plain Language Summary&lt;/a&gt; posted on Functional Ecology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coral reefs support high numbers of fishes which feed on plant material – these reef herbivores include surgeonfish which act as lawnmowers to ‘crop’ turf algae and parrotfish with powerful beaked jaws which ‘scrape’ algae and dirt from the reef.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experiments have shown that cropping and scraping are key ecological functions on coral reefs, helping to maintain reefs in coral-dominated states, particularly after events such as coral bleaching which kill corals and allow fast-growing turf algae and seaweeds to take over. At larger spatial scales – across the Great Barrier Reef, or among Pacific atolls –the biomass of cropping and scraping species can vary greatly, which has been linked to effects of fishing and habitat quality on fish populations.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;image1.jpg&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;School of Singapore parrotfish (Scarus prasiognathos) grazing on an Indo-Pacific reef (credit: Tane Sinclair-Taylor)&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analyses which tie these two approaches together – small-scale feeding rates with large-scale fish biomass estimates – can be used to measure cropping and scraping rates for entire coral reef ecosystems, and so identify influences of fishing and habitat on grazing functions. &lt;a href=&#34;https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1365-2435.13457&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;In our paper&lt;/a&gt;, we generated estimates of grazing functions – cropping and scraping - at 72 coral reefs across the Indo-Pacific, combining underwater feeding observations with fish biomass data from Seychelles, Maldives, the Chagos archipelago, and the Great Barrier Reef. We found that cropping rates depended on reef habitat complexity and the amount of available space on the reef floor, whereas scraping rates were most strongly affected by fishing pressure. These patterns allow us to infer that cropping function will increase in response to loss of corals, and show that scraping function on most reefs is now far below levels observed on unfished, wilderness reefs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Habitat and fishing control grazing potential on coral reefs</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2019-fe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2019-fe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1007/s00338-019-01785-w&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
1. Herbivory is a key process on coral reefs which, through grazing of algae, can help sustain coral-dominated states on frequently-disturbed reefs and reverse macroalgal regime shifts on degraded ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Our understanding of herbivory on reefs is largely founded on feeding observations at small spatial scales, yet the biomass and structure of herbivore populations is more closely linked to processes which can be highly variable across large areas, such as benthic habitat turnover and fishing pressure. Though our understanding of spatiotemporal variation in grazer biomass is well developed, equivalent macroscale approaches to understanding bottom-up and top-down controls on herbivory are lacking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, we integrate underwater survey data of fish abundances from four Indo-Pacific island regions with herbivore feeding observations to estimate grazing rates for two herbivore functions, cropping (which controls turf algae) and scraping (which promotes coral settlement by clearing benthic substrate), for 72 coral reefs. By including a range of reef states, from coral to algal dominance and heavily-fished to remote wilderness areas, we evaluate the influences of benthic habitat and fishing on the grazing rates of fish assemblages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cropping rates were primarily influenced by benthic condition, with cropping maximised on structurally complex reefs with high substratum availability and low macroalgal cover. Fishing was the primary driver of scraping function, with scraping rates depleted at most reefs relative to remote, unfished reefs, though scraping did increase with substratum availability and structural complexity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, benthic and fishing conditions influenced herbivore functioning through their effect on grazer biomass, which was tightly correlated to grazing rates. For a given level of biomass, we show that grazing rates are higher on reefs dominated by small-bodied fishes, suggesting that grazing pressure is greatest when grazer size structure is truncated.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stressors which cause coral declines and clear substrate for turf algae will likely stimulate increases in cropping rates, in both fished and protected areas. In contrast, scraping functions are already impaired at inhabited reefs, particularly where structural complexity has collapsed, indicating that restoration of these key processes will require scraper biomass to be rebuilt towards wilderness levels.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abiotic and biotic controls on coral recovery 16 years after mass
bleaching</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2019-cr/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2019-cr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1007/s00338-019-01831-7&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As climate changes increase heat stress on tropical ecosystems, the long-term persistence of coral reefs requires rapid coral recovery following coral bleaching events. Using the extent of coral cover return to a pre-bleaching baseline as a benchmark, recovery of fast-growing and stress-tolerant coral growth forms suggests that reefs can bounce back between repeated disturbances if given adequate time and protection from anthropogenic disturbances. However, long-term recovery dynamics of coral communities following severe bleaching and mass mortality are limited, particularly for fringing reefs along inhabited coastlines where human stressors may compromise recovery potential. Here, we examine the dynamics and drivers of coral recovery in Seychelles, where 12 reefs returned to pre-bleaching coral cover levels after a severe bleaching event caused &amp;gt; 95% coral mortality. Six reefs with initially low cover ( &amp;lt; 25%) recovered within 7–12 yr and, after 16 yr, exceeded pre-bleaching cover levels by 132–305%. In contrast, six reefs with initially high cover (20–60%) remained at 48–93% of pre-bleaching levels, with recovery projected to take 17–29 yr. Abiotic and historic conditions constrained recovery rates, with the slowest recovery times observed on deep and wave-exposed reefs with high pre-bleaching coral cover. Reefs with high juvenile coral densities and low nitrogen levels recovered fastest, possibly due to the interplay between nutrient enrichment, algal proliferation, and coral recruitment. Our findings emphasize the importance of understanding small-scale variation in recovery potential, whereby recovery times were governed by natural limits on growth rates and modified by coral recruitment and nutrient enrichment. Ultimately, climate-impacted reefs can recover to moderate coral cover levels, but, if bleaching causes repeated high coral mortality, short recovery windows will prevent a return to historic levels of coral dominance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thermal stress induces persistently altered coral reef fish assemblages</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2019-gc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2019-gc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1111/gcb.14704&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Ecological communities are reorganizing in response to warming temperatures. For continuous ocean habitats this reorganization is characterized by large‐scale species redistribution, but for tropical discontinuous habitats such as coral reefs, spatial isolation coupled with strong habitat dependence of fish species imply that turnover and local extinctions are more significant mechanisms. In these systems, transient marine heatwaves are causing coral bleaching and profoundly altering habitat structure, yet despite severe bleaching events becoming more frequent and projections indicating annual severe bleaching by the 2050s at most reefs, long‐term effects on the diversity and structure of fish assemblages remain unclear. Using a 23‐year time series spanning a thermal stress event, we describe and model structural changes and recovery trajectories of fish communities after mass bleaching. Communities changed fundamentally, with the new emergent communities dominated by herbivores and persisting for &amp;gt;15 years, a period exceeding realized and projected intervals between thermal stress events on coral reefs. Reefs which shifted to macroalgal states had the lowest species richness and highest compositional dissimilarity, whereas reefs where live coral recovered exceeded prebleaching fish richness, but remained dissimilar to prebleaching compositions. Given realized and projected frequencies of bleaching events, our results show that fish communities historically associated with coral reefs will not re‐establish, requiring substantial adaptation by managers and resource users.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boom and bust of keystone structure on coral reefs</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/wilson2019-cr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/wilson2019-cr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1007/s00338-019-01785-w&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repeated bouts of coral bleaching threaten the long-term persistence of coral reefs and associated com- munities. Here, we document the short- and long-term impacts of heatwave events on coral and fish assemblages, based on regular surveys of 18 reefs of the granitic islands of Seychelles over 23 yr. Extreme heat events in 1998 and 2016 led to bleaching-associated declines in coral cover, whilst between these years there was an interim period of coral recovery on some reefs. Coral decline and recovery were primarily due to changes in the cover of branching coral, particularly those from the families Acroporidae and Pocilloporidae. Surveys during the 2016 bleaching found that 95% of the 468 Acropora and Pocillopora colonies observed were either bleached or recently dead. The extent of bleaching and subsequent mortality were best explained by a priori assessments of community susceptibility to heat stress. One year later (2017), coral cover had fallen by 70% and average coverage across the 18 reefs was at 6%, sim- ilar to levels recorded in 2005, 7 yr after the 1998 bleaching. Decline in coral following the 2016 bleaching coincided with reduced abundance of fish &amp;lt; 11 cm TL, particularly corallivores, invertivores and mixed diet feeders. These changes are likely to foreshadow more widespread loss once the habitat structure erodes. Accordingly, 7 yr after the 1998 bleaching, when coral skeletons and reef structure had collapsed on some reefs, abundance of both large- and small-bodied fish had declined. We show that fluctuation in the cover of branching coral is positively associated with changes in the abundance of small-bodied fish which contribute to eco- logical processes and high diversity, suggesting branching corals are a keystone structure. Increased frequency of bleaching threatens the capacity of branching corals to fully recover after disturbances, reducing the amplitude of boom bust cycles of these corals and the keystone habitat structure they provide reef fish.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering drivers of juvenile coral density following mass bleaching</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/dajka2019-cj/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/dajka2019-cj/</guid>
      <description>&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1007/s00338-019-01785-w&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thermally induced mass coral bleaching is globally responsible for major losses of coral cover. Coral recovery from mass coral disturbances like the 2016 bleaching event hinges on successful recruitment of new coral colonies to the existing population. Juvenile corals as a life history stage represent survival and growth of new recruits. As such, habitat preferences of juvenile corals and how environmental parameters interact to drive coral recovery following a mass bleaching disturbance are important research areas. To expand our knowledge on this topic, we compared juvenile coral densities from before the 2016 bleaching event with those after the disturbance and identified abiotic and biotic characteristics of 21 reefs in the inner Seychelles that predict juvenile coral densities. Our results show that following the 2016 bleaching event, juvenile coral densities were significantly reduced by about 70%, with a particularly large decline in juvenile Acropora. Macroalgae present a large obstacle to survival of juvenile corals in a post-bleaching setting, but their influence varies as a function of herbivore biomass, reef structure, and reef type. Higher biomass of herbivorous fish weakens the negative effect of macroalgae on juvenile corals, and structural complexity on granitic reefs is a strong positive predictor of juvenile coral density. However, structural complexity on carbonate or patch reefs was negatively related to juvenile coral density, highlighting the impor- tance of considering interactive terms in analyses. Our study emphasises the importance of habitat for juvenile coral abundance at both fine and seascape scales, adding to the literature on drivers of reef rebound potential following severe coral bleaching.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
