<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>James PW Robinson on James PW Robinson</title>
    <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in James PW Robinson on James PW Robinson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Trophic distribution of nutrient production in coral reef fisheries</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2023-pb/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2023-pb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-badge-details=&#39;right&#39; data-altmetric-id=&#34;120363675&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coral reef fisheries supply nutritious catch to tropical coastal communities, where the quality of reef seafood is determined by both the rate of biomass pro- duction and nutritional value of reef fishes. Yet our understanding of reef fisheries typically uses targets of total reef fish biomass rather than individual growth (i.e. biomass production) and nutrient content (i.e. nutritional value of reef fish), limiting the ability of management to sustain the productivity of nutritious catches. Here, we use modelled growth coefficients and nutrient concentrations to develop a new metric of nutrient productivity of coral reef fishes. We then evaluate this metric with underwater visual surveys of reef fish assemblages from four tropical countries to examine nutrient productivity of reef fish food webs. Species’ growth coefficients were associated with nutri- ents that vary with body size (calcium, iron, selenium and zinc), but not total nutrient density. When integrated with fish abundance data, we find that herbivorous species typically dominate standing biomass, biomass turnover and nutrient production on coral reefs. Such bottom-heavy trophic distri- butions of nutrients were consistent across gradients of fishing pressure and benthic composition. We conclude that management restrictions that promote sustainability of herbivores and other low trophic-level species can sustain biomass and nutrient production from reef fisheries that is critical to the food security of over 500 million people in the tropics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Small pelagic fish supply abundant and affordable micronutrients to low- and middle-income countries</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-nf/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-nf/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-altmetric-id=&#34;139558389&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wild-caught fish provide an irreplaceable source of essential nutrients in food-insecure places. Fishers catch thousands of species, yet the diversity
 of aquatic foods is often categorized homogeneously as ‘fish’, obscuring an understanding of which species supply affordable, nutritious and abundant food. Here, we use catch, economic and nutrient data on 2,348 species to identify the most affordable and nutritious fish in 39 low- and middle-income countries. We find that a 100 g portion of fish cost between 10 and 30% of the cheapest daily diet, with small pelagic fish (herring, sardine, anchovy) being the cheapest nutritious fish in 72% of countries. In sub-Saharan Africa, where nutrient deficiencies are rising, &amp;lt;20% of small pelagic catch would meet recommended dietary fish intakes for all children (6 months to 4 years old) living near to water bodies. Nutrition-sensitive policies that ensure local supplies and promote consumption of wild-caught fish could help address nutrient deficiencies in vulnerable populations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Navigating sustainability and health trade-offs in global seafood systems</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-erl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-erl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;donut&#34; data-altmetric-id=&#34;138788475&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seafood is expected to play a key role in improving access to healthy diets while providing food products with relatively low rates of greenhouse gas emissions. However, both nutrients and carbon footprints vary among species and production methods, and seafood consumption is further influenced by price and consumer preference, such that it is unclear which species are best placed to provide low-carbon nutritious seafood. Here, we compare the nutrient content and &amp;lsquo;farm-gate&amp;rsquo;  greenhouse gas emissions of 106 fished and farmed seafood products  globally and, using seafood production data, assess the nutritional  value, carbon emissions, sustainability, affordability, and availability of seafood available to UK consumers. Most seafood products are more nutritious and emit lower greenhouse gases than terrestrial animal-source foods. Among seafoods, small pelagic fishes and bivalves met recommended intakes for 3-4 essential dietary nutrients at the lowest emissions, whereas beef and lamb had the highest emissions per recommended nutrient target. For seafood products relevant to UK markets and consumers, Atlantic mackerel had the highest availability  (landings) of all wild-caught UK seafood and lowest carbon footprint of  all finfish, with one fillet portion exceeding recommended intakes of five nutrients (iodine, selenium, omega-3 fatty acids, vitamins B12 and D). We found that price and sustainability of UK seafood, both factors  in consumer demand, had considerable trade-offs with nutrients, carbon footprint, and availability. Farmed salmon, for example, were produced in large volumes but were relatively more expensive and less nutritious than other seafood, whereas highly nutritious, low-carbon farmed mussels had limited production volumes. The UK&amp;rsquo;s seafood system is therefore  not currently optimised to produce nutritious, low-carbon seafood in large amounts. Policies that promote local consumption of affordable species already produced in high volumes, such as mackerel, could improve intakes of nutrients that are deficient in the UK population, at relatively low environmental cost.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Safeguarding nutrients from coral reefs under climate change</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/mellin2022-ne/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/mellin2022-ne/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-badge-details=&#39;right&#39; data-altmetric-id=&#34;136744110&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sustainability of coral reef fisheries is jeopardized by complex and interacting socio-ecological stressors that undermine their contribution to food and nutrition security. Climate change has emerged as one of the key stressors threatening coral reefs and their fish-associated services. How fish nutrient concentrations respond to warming oceans remains unclear but these responses are probably affected by both direct (metabolism and trophodynamics) and indirect (habitat and species range shifts) effects. Climate-driven coral habitat loss can cause changes in fish abundance and biomass, revealing potential winners and losers among major fisheries targets that can be predicted using ecological indicators and biological traits. A critical next step is to extend research focused on the quantity of available food (fish biomass) to also consider its nutritional quality, which is relevant to progress in the fields of food security and malnutrition. Biological traits are robust predictors of fish nutrient content and thus potentially indicate how climate-driven changes are expected to impact nutrient availability within future food webs on coral reefs. Here, we outline future research priorities and an anticipatory framework towards sustainable reef fisheries contributing to nutrition-sensitive food systems in a warming ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maximising sustainable nutrient production from coupled fisheries-aquaculture systems</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/willer2022-ps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/willer2022-ps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-badge-details=&#39;right&#39; data-altmetric-id=&#34;123889310&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aquaculture expansion is expected to meet growing demand for sustainable animal-source foods. Yet marine-fed species already require millions of tonnes of wild-caught fish for feed, over 90% of which are nutritious  food-grade species. Allocating feed fish for human consumption could  reduce pressure on marine resources while increasing seafood production. We examine micronutrient flows (the transfer of micronutrients from  feed to fish) in Scotland’s farmed salmon industry, which is  particularly reliant on marine feeds, to show that 1–49% of essential  dietary minerals and fatty acids available in wild fish are retained in  farmed salmon. Using three alternative production scenarios we show that reducing marine feeds in salmon production and allocating wild-caught  feed fish for human consumption could produce more nutritious seafood  and leave 66–82% of feed fish in the sea. Using global data on  marine-fed aquaculture production, we show that removing wild-caught  fish from salmonid production could leave 3.7 Mt fish in the sea while  increasing global seafood production by 6.1 Mt.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing fisheries for maximum nutrient yield</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-ff/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-ff/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-badge-details=&#39;right&#39; data-altmetric-id=&#34;123231360&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wild-caught fish are a bioavailable source of nutritious food that, if  managed strategically, could enhance diet quality for billions of  people. However, optimising nutrient production from the sea has not  been a priority, hindering development of nutrition-sensitive policies.  With fisheries management increasingly effective at rebuilding stocks  and regulating sustainable fishing, we can now begin to integrate  nutritional outcomes within existing management frameworks. Here, we  develop a conceptual foundation for managing fisheries for multispecies  Maximum Nutrient Yield (mMNY). We empirically test our approach using  size-based models of North Sea and Baltic Sea fisheries and show that  mMNY is predicted by the relative contribution of nutritious species to  total catch and their vulnerability to fishing, leading to trade-offs  between catch and specific nutrients. Simulated nutrient yield curves  suggest that vitamin D, which is deficient in Northern European diets,  was underfished at fishing levels that returned maximum catch weights.  Analysis of global catch data shows there is scope for nutrient yields  from most of the world&amp;rsquo;s marine fisheries to be enhanced through  nutrient-sensitive fisheries management. With nutrient composition data  now widely available, we expect our mMNY framework to motivate  development of nutrient-based reference points in specific contexts,  such as data-limited fisheries. Managing for mMNY alongside policies  that promote access to fish could help close nutrient gaps for coastal  populations, maximising the contribution of wild-caught fish to global  food and nutrition security.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate-induced increases in micronutrient availability for coral reef fisheries</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-oe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-oe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-badge-details=&#39;right&#39; data-altmetric-id=&#34;120363675&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate change is transforming coral reefs, threatening supply of  essential dietary micronutrients from small-scale fisheries to tropical  coastal communities. Yet the nutritional value of reef fisheries and  climate impacts on micronutrient availability remain unclear, hindering  efforts to sustain food and nutrition security. Here, we measure  nutrient content in coral reef fishes in Seychelles and show that reef  fish are important sources of selenium and zinc and contain levels of  calcium, iron, and omega-3 fatty acids comparable with other  animal-source foods. Using experimental fishing, we demonstrate that  iron and zinc are enriched in fishes caught on regime-shifted macroalgal habitats, whereas selenium and omega-3 varied among species. We find  substantial increases in nutrients available to fisheries over two  decades following coral bleaching, particularly for iron and zinc after  macroalgal regime shifts. Our findings indicate that, if managed  sustainably, coral reef fisheries could remain important micronutrient  sources along tropical coastlines despite escalating climate impacts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Secure local aquatic food systems in the face of declining coral reefs</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/hicks2021-oe/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/hicks2021-oe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;   10.1016/j.oneear.2021.08.023&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coral reefs are harbingers of environmental change. In this issue of OneEarth, Eddy et al. analyze long-termdeclines in reef condition and fish catches. Here, we highlight how policies that secure coral reefs as localfood systems can safeguard diverse, nutrient rich diets and support vulnerable social-ecological systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Micronutrient supply from global marine fisheries under climate change and overfishing</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/maire2021-cb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/maire2021-cb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-badge-details=&#39;right&#39; data-altmetric-id=&#34;110037730&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;   10.1016/j.cub.2021.06.067&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fish are rich in bioavailable micronutrients, such as zinc and iron, deficiencies of which are a global food security concern.Global marine fisheries yields are threatened by climate change and overfishing, yet understanding of how these stressors affect the nutrients available from fisheries is lacking. Here, using global assessments of micronutrient content and fisheries catch data, we investigate how the vulnerability status of marine fish species may translate into vulnerability of micronutrient availability at scales of both individual species and entire fishery assemblages for 157 countries. We further quantify the micronutrient evenness of catches to identify countries where interventions can optimize micronutrient supply. Our global analysis, including &amp;gt;800 marine fish species, reveals that, at a species level, micronutrient availability and vulnerability to both climate change and overfishing varies greatly, with tropical species displaying a positive co-tolerance, indicating greater persistence to both stressors at a community level. Global fisheries catches had relatively low nutritional vulnerability to fishing. Catches with higher species richness tend to be nutrient dense and evenly distributed but are more vulnerable to climate change, with 40% of countries displaying high vulnerability. Countries with high prevalence of inadequate micronutrient intake tend to have the most nutrient-dense catches, but these same fisheries are highly vulnerable to climate change,with relatively lower capacity to adapt. Our analysis highlights the need to consolidate fisheries, climate, and food policies to secure the sustainable contribution of fish-derived micronutrients to food and nutrition security.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changing role of coral reef marine reserves in a warming climate</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/graham2020-nc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/graham2020-nc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1038/s41467-020-15863-z&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Coral reef ecosystems are among the first to fundamentally change in structure due to climate change, which leads to questioning of whether decades of knowledge regarding reef management is still applicable. Here we assess ecological responses to no-take marine reserves over two decades, spanning a major climate-driven coral bleaching event. Pre-bleaching reserve responses were consistent with a large literature, with higher coral cover, more species of fish, and greater fish biomass, particularly of upper trophic levels. However, in the 16 years following coral mortality, reserve effects were absent for the reef benthos, and greatly diminished for fish species richness. Positive fish biomass effects persisted, but the groups of fish benefiting from marine reserves profoundly changed, with low trophic level herbivores dominating the responses. These findings highlight that while marine reserves still have important roles on coral reefs in the face of climate change, the species and functional groups they benefit will be substantially altered.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tropical fisheries: does limiting international trade protect local people and marine life?</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/post/trop-trade-conversation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/post/trop-trade-conversation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Repost of &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/tropical-fisheries-does-limiting-international-trade-protect-local-people-and-marine-life-133403&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;this article in The Conservation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tropical island states enjoy global demand for their seafood, but many have growing populations and hungry tourists to feed. &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/local-communities-play-outsized-but-overlooked-role-in-global-fisheries-123143&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Their fisheries&lt;/a&gt; are often unregulated and lack dSeychelles and Palau&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People in the Seychelles eat more seafood than &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fao.org/3/a-br801e.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;any other country in Africa&lt;/a&gt;, averaging 60kg per person per year. But as many seafood species,  including bourzwa, have become valuable exports, their prices have  jumped, making some popular fish unaffordable for many locals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bourzwa are caught on the Mahè plateau, a productive fishing ground  covering about 41,000km², where Seychellois fishermen catch over 1,000  tonnes of fish each year. These fisheries target a diverse group of  species, including groupers, jacks and barracuda, as well as bourzwa. But the red snapper fisheries that target bourzwa are in trouble – our  study found that catches have halved since 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/320130/original/file-20200312-111300-1tgehjy.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;fit=clip&#34; alt=&#34;img&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​              Local fishermen offload their catch on Mahé island, Seychelles.              &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shutterstock.com/image-photo/mahe-island-seychelles15th-december-local-fisherman-177878093&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Jerome Stubbs/Shutterstock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our research showed that all of these species are in decline, with an average 65% drop in catch rates over 27 years. These catch declines coincided with a quadrupling of the fishing fleet, with fishers spending more time fishing, using more fuel, and expanding their fishing grounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Banning exports might reduce fishing pressure on bourzwa. But local markets buy over four times as much snapper than is exported, suggesting that prices are unlikely to drop. A ban could also shift fishing effort onto other export species, such as long-lived groupers that are vulnerable to overfishing, and disproportionately disadvantage bourzwa  fishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also found that fishers who caught lots of different fish, rather  than relying on one species, had bigger catches and higher revenues. Alongside an export ban, the government of Seychelles could bring in regulation to encourage fishers to diversify what they catch. Spreading fishing effort across different fish stocks can help vulnerable species like bourzwa recover, while also protecting livelihoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, much of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0308597X19301782?via%3Dihub&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;fish consumed in Palau is caught by foreign industrial vessels&lt;/a&gt;. Palau’s new sanctuary excluded this offshore fleet, but it  inadvertently shifted fishing pressure inshore. As a result, the marine  sanctuary has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/feb/27/palaus-marine-sanctuary-backfires-leading-to-increased-consumption-of-reef-fish&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;increased pressure on coral reef species&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/320133/original/file-20200312-111232-1ow4mcb.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;fit=clip&#34; alt=&#34;img&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​              Jacks on a coral reef in Palau.              &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shutterstock.com/image-photo/mackerels-pacific-ocean-palau-29856577&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Marcus Efler/Shutterstock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seychellois fish markets also depend on coral reefs, which have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-018-0715-z&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;remained productive despite mass coral bleaching&lt;/a&gt;. It’s unclear if a snapper export ban would increase fishing on  Seychelles’ reefs, but Palau’s experiment shows the importance of  understanding which species and ecosystems feed coastal communities  before making big policy decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reducing seafood exports might help reduce pressure on tropical  fisheries, but these bans won’t make the fisheries sustainable on their  own, and may even be overruled by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wto.org/english/tratop_e/markacc_e/qr_e.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;World Trade Organisation rules&lt;/a&gt;. Fishing regulations are a more effective way of protecting them from  international trade. These should help tropical countries to maximise  the diversity of fish their fisheries catch, protecting particular fish  stocks from plunder and certain fishers from poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For fishing bans to succeed, governments need to thoroughly  understand the local and international demand on different fisheries and ecosystems, to anticipate knock-on effects for the people and marine  life they support.ata on the exploitation status of fish  populations. Without this information, some countries are preparing to  protect them by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nation.sc/articles/3547/2020-state-of-the-nation-address-by-president-danny-faure-on-february-20-2020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;limiting international seafood trade&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2020, Danny Faure, president of the Seychelles, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nation.sc/articles/3547/2020-state-of-the-nation-address-by-president-danny-faure-on-february-20-2020&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;announced an export ban&lt;/a&gt; on “bourzwa”, a tropical red snapper that has doubled in price over the last decade. Meanwhile, on January 1, 2020, Palau introduced a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pewtrusts.org/en/research-and-analysis/articles/2020/01/01/palau-national-marine-sanctuary-goes-into-effect&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;new marine sanctuary&lt;/a&gt;, banning commercial fishing in 80% of its waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Seychelles’ export ban and Palau’s marine sanctuary are designed to protect domestic seafood supplies and conserve ecosystems, such as  coral reefs, that are vulnerable to climate change. The international  seafood trade can enrich tropical islands in the short term, as &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/eu-targets-fragile-west-african-fish-stocks-despite-protection-laws-125679&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;foreign fleets pay for permission to fish&lt;/a&gt; in their waters. But, as islands off West Africa such as Cape Verde  have found, the long-term result can be depleted fish stocks – &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/nigerias-depleting-fish-stocks-may-pose-a-threat-to-regional-security-105168&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;with over half of the region’s fisheries overfished&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are seafood export bans the solution? &lt;a href=&#34;https://advances.sciencemag.org/content/6/8/eaaz0587&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Our research&lt;/a&gt; using rare long-term catch data from the Seychelles suggests that these bans could have unexpected consequences, for fish stocks and the livelihoods of people they’re designed to protect.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversification insulates fisher catch and revenue in heavily exploited tropical fisheries.</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2020-sa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2020-sa/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;div data-badge-details=&#34;right&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-doi=&#34;10.1126/sciadv.aaz0587&#34; data-hide-no-mentions=&#34;true&#34; class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Declines in commercial landings and increases in fishing fleet power have raised concerns over the continued provisioning of nutritional and economic services by tropical wild fisheries. Yet, because tropical fisheries are often data-poor, mechanisms that might buffer fishers to declines are not understood. This data scarcity undermines fisheries management, making tropical fishing livelihoods particularly vulnerable to changes in marine resources. We use high-resolution fisheries data from Seychelles to understand how fishing strategy (catch diversification) influences catch rates and revenues of individual fishing vessels. We show that average catch weight decreased by 65% over 27 years, with declines in all nine species groups coinciding with increases in fishing effort. However, for individual vessels, catch diversity was associated with larger catches and higher fishing revenues and with slower catch declines from 1990 to 2016. Management strategies should maximize catch diversity in data-poor tropical fisheries to help secure nutritional security while protecting fishing livelihoods.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accounting for the bin structure of data removes bias when fitting size spectra</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/edwards2020-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/edwards2020-me/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Size spectra are recommended tools for detecting the response of marine communities to fishing or to management measures. A size spectrum succinctly describes how a property, such as abundance or biomass, varies with body size in a community. Required data are often collected in binned form, such as numbers of individuals in 1 cm length bins. Numerous methods have been employed to fit size spectra, but most give biased estimates when tested on simulated data, and none account for the data’s bin structure (breakpoints of bins). Here, we used 8 methods to fit an annual size-spectrum exponent, b, to an example data set (30 yr of the North Sea International Bottom Trawl Survey). The methods gave conflicting conclusions regarding b declining (the size spectrum steepening) through time, and so any resulting advice to ecosystem managers will be highly dependent upon the method used. Using simulated data, we showed that ignoring the bin structure gives biased estimates of b, even for high-resolution data. However, our extended likelihood method, which explicitly accounts for the bin structure, accurately estimated b and its confidence intervals, even for coarsely collected data. We developed a novel visualisation method that accounts for the bin structure and associated uncertainty, provide recommendations concerning different data types and have created an R package (sizeSpectra) to reproduce all results and encourage use of our methods. This work is also relevant to wider applications where a power-law distribution (the underlying distribution for a size spectrum) is fitted to binned data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climatic and local stressor interactions threaten tropical forests and coral reefs</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/franca2020-pt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/franca2020-pt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;https://d1bxh8uas1mnw7.cloudfront.net/assets/embed.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;altmetric-embed&#34; data-badge-type=&#34;medium-donut&#34; data-badge-details=&#39;right&#39; data-altmetric-id=&#34;120363675&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tropical forests and coral reefs host a disproportionately large share of global biodiversity and provide ecosystem functions and services used by millions of people. Yet, ongoing climate change is leading to an increase in frequency and magnitude of extreme climatic events in the tropics, which, in combination with other local human disturbances, is leading to unprecedented negative ecological consequences for tropical forests and coral reefs. Here, we provide an overview of how and where climate extremes are affecting the most biodiverse ecosystems on Earth and summarize how interactions between global, regional and local stressors are affecting tropical forest and coral reef systems through impacts on biodiversity and ecosystem resilience. We also discuss some key challenges and opportunities to promote mitigation and adaptation to a changing climate at local and global scales.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fishing and habitat control grazing potential across 72 coral reefs</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/post/func-grazing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/post/func-grazing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is my &lt;a href=&#34;https://fesummaries.wordpress.com/2019/09/26/fishing-and-habitat-quality-control-grazing-functions-across-72-coral-reefs/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Plain Language Summary&lt;/a&gt; posted on Functional Ecology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coral reefs support high numbers of fishes which feed on plant material – these reef herbivores include surgeonfish which act as lawnmowers to ‘crop’ turf algae and parrotfish with powerful beaked jaws which ‘scrape’ algae and dirt from the reef.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experiments have shown that cropping and scraping are key ecological functions on coral reefs, helping to maintain reefs in coral-dominated states, particularly after events such as coral bleaching which kill corals and allow fast-growing turf algae and seaweeds to take over. At larger spatial scales – across the Great Barrier Reef, or among Pacific atolls –the biomass of cropping and scraping species can vary greatly, which has been linked to effects of fishing and habitat quality on fish populations.&lt;/p&gt;




&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;image1.jpg&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;h4&gt;School of Singapore parrotfish (Scarus prasiognathos) grazing on an Indo-Pacific reef (credit: Tane Sinclair-Taylor)&lt;/h4&gt;
  
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Analyses which tie these two approaches together – small-scale feeding rates with large-scale fish biomass estimates – can be used to measure cropping and scraping rates for entire coral reef ecosystems, and so identify influences of fishing and habitat on grazing functions. &lt;a href=&#34;https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1365-2435.13457&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;In our paper&lt;/a&gt;, we generated estimates of grazing functions – cropping and scraping - at 72 coral reefs across the Indo-Pacific, combining underwater feeding observations with fish biomass data from Seychelles, Maldives, the Chagos archipelago, and the Great Barrier Reef. We found that cropping rates depended on reef habitat complexity and the amount of available space on the reef floor, whereas scraping rates were most strongly affected by fishing pressure. These patterns allow us to infer that cropping function will increase in response to loss of corals, and show that scraping function on most reefs is now far below levels observed on unfished, wilderness reefs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
