<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2 on James PW Robinson</title>
    <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication_types/2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2 on James PW Robinson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication_types/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Trophic distribution of nutrient production in coral reef fisheries</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2023-pb/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2023-pb/</guid>
      <description>Coral reef fisheries supply nutritious catch to tropical coastal communities, where the quality of reef seafood is determined by both the rate of biomass pro- duction and nutritional value of reef fishes. Yet our understanding of reef fisheries typically uses targets of total reef fish biomass rather than individual growth (i.e. biomass production) and nutrient content (i.e. nutritional value of reef fish), limiting the ability of management to sustain the productivity of nutritious catches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Small pelagic fish supply abundant and affordable micronutrients to low- and middle-income countries</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-nf/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-nf/</guid>
      <description>Wild-caught fish provide an irreplaceable source of essential nutrients in food-insecure places. Fishers catch thousands of species, yet the diversity of aquatic foods is often categorized homogeneously as ‘fish’, obscuring an understanding of which species supply affordable, nutritious and abundant food. Here, we use catch, economic and nutrient data on 2,348 species to identify the most affordable and nutritious fish in 39 low- and middle-income countries. We find that a 100 g portion of fish cost between 10 and 30% of the cheapest daily diet, with small pelagic fish (herring, sardine, anchovy) being the cheapest nutritious fish in 72% of countries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Navigating sustainability and health trade-offs in global seafood systems</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-erl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-erl/</guid>
      <description>Seafood is expected to play a key role in improving access to healthy diets while providing food products with relatively low rates of greenhouse gas emissions. However, both nutrients and carbon footprints vary among species and production methods, and seafood consumption is further influenced by price and consumer preference, such that it is unclear which species are best placed to provide low-carbon nutritious seafood. Here, we compare the nutrient content and &amp;lsquo;farm-gate&amp;rsquo; greenhouse gas emissions of 106 fished and farmed seafood products globally and, using seafood production data, assess the nutritional value, carbon emissions, sustainability, affordability, and availability of seafood available to UK consumers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Safeguarding nutrients from coral reefs under climate change</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/mellin2022-ne/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/mellin2022-ne/</guid>
      <description>The sustainability of coral reef fisheries is jeopardized by complex and interacting socio-ecological stressors that undermine their contribution to food and nutrition security. Climate change has emerged as one of the key stressors threatening coral reefs and their fish-associated services. How fish nutrient concentrations respond to warming oceans remains unclear but these responses are probably affected by both direct (metabolism and trophodynamics) and indirect (habitat and species range shifts) effects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maximising sustainable nutrient production from coupled fisheries-aquaculture systems</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/willer2022-ps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/willer2022-ps/</guid>
      <description>Aquaculture expansion is expected to meet growing demand for sustainable animal-source foods. Yet marine-fed species already require millions of tonnes of wild-caught fish for feed, over 90% of which are nutritious food-grade species. Allocating feed fish for human consumption could reduce pressure on marine resources while increasing seafood production. We examine micronutrient flows (the transfer of micronutrients from feed to fish) in Scotland’s farmed salmon industry, which is particularly reliant on marine feeds, to show that 1–49% of essential dietary minerals and fatty acids available in wild fish are retained in farmed salmon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing fisheries for maximum nutrient yield</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-ff/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-ff/</guid>
      <description>Wild-caught fish are a bioavailable source of nutritious food that, if managed strategically, could enhance diet quality for billions of people. However, optimising nutrient production from the sea has not been a priority, hindering development of nutrition-sensitive policies. With fisheries management increasingly effective at rebuilding stocks and regulating sustainable fishing, we can now begin to integrate nutritional outcomes within existing management frameworks. Here, we develop a conceptual foundation for managing fisheries for multispecies Maximum Nutrient Yield (mMNY).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate-induced increases in micronutrient availability for coral reef fisheries</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-oe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2022-oe/</guid>
      <description>Climate change is transforming coral reefs, threatening supply of essential dietary micronutrients from small-scale fisheries to tropical coastal communities. Yet the nutritional value of reef fisheries and climate impacts on micronutrient availability remain unclear, hindering efforts to sustain food and nutrition security. Here, we measure nutrient content in coral reef fishes in Seychelles and show that reef fish are important sources of selenium and zinc and contain levels of calcium, iron, and omega-3 fatty acids comparable with other animal-source foods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Secure local aquatic food systems in the face of declining coral reefs</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/hicks2021-oe/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/hicks2021-oe/</guid>
      <description>Coral reefs are harbingers of environmental change. In this issue of OneEarth, Eddy et al. analyze long-termdeclines in reef condition and fish catches. Here, we highlight how policies that secure coral reefs as localfood systems can safeguard diverse, nutrient rich diets and support vulnerable social-ecological systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Micronutrient supply from global marine fisheries under climate change and overfishing</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/maire2021-cb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/maire2021-cb/</guid>
      <description>Fish are rich in bioavailable micronutrients, such as zinc and iron, deficiencies of which are a global food security concern.Global marine fisheries yields are threatened by climate change and overfishing, yet understanding of how these stressors affect the nutrients available from fisheries is lacking. Here, using global assessments of micronutrient content and fisheries catch data, we investigate how the vulnerability status of marine fish species may translate into vulnerability of micronutrient availability at scales of both individual species and entire fishery assemblages for 157 countries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changing role of coral reef marine reserves in a warming climate</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/graham2020-nc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/graham2020-nc/</guid>
      <description>Coral reef ecosystems are among the first to fundamentally change in structure due to climate change, which leads to questioning of whether decades of knowledge regarding reef management is still applicable. Here we assess ecological responses to no-take marine reserves over two decades, spanning a major climate-driven coral bleaching event. Pre-bleaching reserve responses were consistent with a large literature, with higher coral cover, more species of fish, and greater fish biomass, particularly of upper trophic levels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversification insulates fisher catch and revenue in heavily exploited tropical fisheries.</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2020-sa/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2020-sa/</guid>
      <description>Declines in commercial landings and increases in fishing fleet power have raised concerns over the continued provisioning of nutritional and economic services by tropical wild fisheries. Yet, because tropical fisheries are often data-poor, mechanisms that might buffer fishers to declines are not understood. This data scarcity undermines fisheries management, making tropical fishing livelihoods particularly vulnerable to changes in marine resources. We use high-resolution fisheries data from Seychelles to understand how fishing strategy (catch diversification) influences catch rates and revenues of individual fishing vessels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accounting for the bin structure of data removes bias when fitting size spectra</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/edwards2020-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/edwards2020-me/</guid>
      <description>Size spectra are recommended tools for detecting the response of marine communities to fishing or to management measures. A size spectrum succinctly describes how a property, such as abundance or biomass, varies with body size in a community. Required data are often collected in binned form, such as numbers of individuals in 1 cm length bins. Numerous methods have been employed to fit size spectra, but most give biased estimates when tested on simulated data, and none account for the data’s bin structure (breakpoints of bins).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climatic and local stressor interactions threaten tropical forests and coral reefs</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/franca2020-pt/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/franca2020-pt/</guid>
      <description>Tropical forests and coral reefs host a disproportionately large share of global biodiversity and provide ecosystem functions and services used by millions of people. Yet, ongoing climate change is leading to an increase in frequency and magnitude of extreme climatic events in the tropics, which, in combination with other local human disturbances, is leading to unprecedented negative ecological consequences for tropical forests and coral reefs. Here, we provide an overview of how and where climate extremes are affecting the most biodiverse ecosystems on Earth and summarize how interactions between global, regional and local stressors are affecting tropical forest and coral reef systems through impacts on biodiversity and ecosystem resilience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Habitat and fishing control grazing potential on coral reefs</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2019-fe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2019-fe/</guid>
      <description>1. Herbivory is a key process on coral reefs which, through grazing of algae, can help sustain coral-dominated states on frequently-disturbed reefs and reverse macroalgal regime shifts on degraded ones.
 Our understanding of herbivory on reefs is largely founded on feeding observations at small spatial scales, yet the biomass and structure of herbivore populations is more closely linked to processes which can be highly variable across large areas, such as benthic habitat turnover and fishing pressure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abiotic and biotic controls on coral recovery 16 years after mass
bleaching</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2019-cr/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2019-cr/</guid>
      <description>As climate changes increase heat stress on tropical ecosystems, the long-term persistence of coral reefs requires rapid coral recovery following coral bleaching events. Using the extent of coral cover return to a pre-bleaching baseline as a benchmark, recovery of fast-growing and stress-tolerant coral growth forms suggests that reefs can bounce back between repeated disturbances if given adequate time and protection from anthropogenic disturbances. However, long-term recovery dynamics of coral communities following severe bleaching and mass mortality are limited, particularly for fringing reefs along inhabited coastlines where human stressors may compromise recovery potential.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thermal stress induces persistently altered coral reef fish assemblages</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2019-gc/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2019-gc/</guid>
      <description>Ecological communities are reorganizing in response to warming temperatures. For continuous ocean habitats this reorganization is characterized by large‐scale species redistribution, but for tropical discontinuous habitats such as coral reefs, spatial isolation coupled with strong habitat dependence of fish species imply that turnover and local extinctions are more significant mechanisms. In these systems, transient marine heatwaves are causing coral bleaching and profoundly altering habitat structure, yet despite severe bleaching events becoming more frequent and projections indicating annual severe bleaching by the 2050s at most reefs, long‐term effects on the diversity and structure of fish assemblages remain unclear.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boom and bust of keystone structure on coral reefs</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/wilson2019-cr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/wilson2019-cr/</guid>
      <description>Repeated bouts of coral bleaching threaten the long-term persistence of coral reefs and associated com- munities. Here, we document the short- and long-term impacts of heatwave events on coral and fish assemblages, based on regular surveys of 18 reefs of the granitic islands of Seychelles over 23 yr. Extreme heat events in 1998 and 2016 led to bleaching-associated declines in coral cover, whilst between these years there was an interim period of coral recovery on some reefs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering drivers of juvenile coral density following mass bleaching</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/dajka2019-cj/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/dajka2019-cj/</guid>
      <description>Thermally induced mass coral bleaching is globally responsible for major losses of coral cover. Coral recovery from mass coral disturbances like the 2016 bleaching event hinges on successful recruitment of new coral colonies to the existing population. Juvenile corals as a life history stage represent survival and growth of new recruits. As such, habitat preferences of juvenile corals and how environmental parameters interact to drive coral recovery following a mass bleaching disturbance are important research areas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Productive instability of coral reef fisheries after climate-driven regime shifts</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2018-qs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2018-qs/</guid>
      <description>Tropical coastal communities are highly reliant on coral reefs, which provide nutrition and employment for millions of people. Climate-driven coral bleaching events are fundamentally changing coral reef ecosystems and are predicted to reduce produc- tivity of coral reef fish and fisheries, with significant implications for food security and livelihoods. Yet evidence of long-term bleaching impacts on coral reef fishery productivity is lacking. Here, we analyse over 20 years of fish abundance, catch and habitat data to assess long-term impacts of climate-driven coral mass mortality and regime shifts on nearshore artisanal coral reef fisheries in the Seychelles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental conditions and herbivore biomass determine coral
reef benthic community composition: implications for quantitative
baselines</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2018-tf/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2018-tf/</guid>
      <description>Our ability to understand natural constraints on coral reef benthic communities requires quantitative assessment of the relative strengths of abiotic and biotic processes across large spatial scales. Here, we combine underwater images, visual censuses and remote sensing data for 1,566 sites across 34 islands spanning the central- western Pacific Ocean, to empirically assess the relative roles of abiotic and grazing processes in determining the prevalence of calcifying organisms and fleshy algae on coral reefs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Climate Change Research With Open Science</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/tai2018-dd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/tai2018-dd/</guid>
      <description>Climate change research aims to understand global environmental change and how it will impact nature and society. The broad scope of climate change impacts means that successful adaptation and mitigation efforts will require an unprecedented collaboration effort that unites diverse disciplines and is able to rapidly respond to evolving climate issues (IPCC, 2014). However, to achieve this aim, climate change research practices need updating: key research findings remain behind journal paywalls, and scientific progress can be impeded by low levels of reproducibility and transparency (Ellison, 2010; Morueta-Holme et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fishing degrades size structure of coral reef fish communities</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2017-xm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2017-xm/</guid>
      <description>Fishing pressure on coral reef ecosystems has been frequently linked to reductions of large fishes and reef fish biomass. Associated impacts on overall community structure are, however, less clear. In size-structured aquatic ecosystems, fishing impacts are commonly quantified using size spectra, which describe the distribution of individual body sizes within a community. We examined the size spectra and biomass of coral reef fish communities at 38 US- affiliated Pacific islands that ranged in human presence from near pristine to human population centers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing and recommending methods for fitting size spectra to data</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/edwards2017-wp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/edwards2017-wp/</guid>
      <description>The size spectrum of an ecological community characterizes how a property, such as abundance or biomass, varies with body size. Size spectra are often used as ecosystem indicators of marine systems. They have been fitted to data from various sources, including groundfish trawl surveys, visual surveys of fish in kelp forests and coral reefs, sediment samples of benthic invertebrates and satellite remote sensing of chlorophyll.
 Over the past decades, several methods have been used to fit size spectra to data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trophic roles determine coral reef fish community size structure</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2016-wg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2016-wg/</guid>
      <description>Relationships between abundance – body size and trophic position – body size can reveal size structuring in food webs and test ecological theory. Although there is considerable evidence of size structuring in temperate aquatic food webs, little is known about the structure of tropical coral reef food webs. Here, we use underwater visual-census data and nitrogen stable isotope analysis to test if coral reef fish communities (i) are size structured and (ii) follow metabolic scaling rules.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimation of predator-prey mass ratios using stable isotopes:
sources of errors</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/hertz2014-pw/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/hertz2014-pw/</guid>
      <description>In aquatic systems, the ratio of predator mass to prey mass (PPMR) is an important constraint on food web structure, and has been correlated with environmental stability. One common approach of estimating PPMR uses nitrogen stable isotopes (δ15N) as an indicator of trophic position, under the assumption that the discrimination between diet and tissue is constant with increasing diet δ15N (an additive approach). However, recent studies have shown that this assumption may not be valid and that there is a negative trend between the δ15N of the diet and the discrimination value (a scaled approach).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The limitations of diversity metrics in directing global marine
conservation</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2014-ow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2014-ow/</guid>
      <description>Biodiversity hotspots have been used extensively in setting conservation priorities for marine ecosystems. A recent Nature publication claims to have uncovered new latitudinal gradients in the evenness of reef communities and new reef hotspots based on functional diversity. Simulation models show that the purported evenness gradient is a mathematical inevitability of differences in species richness and detectability between vastly different marine ecosystems, namely ‘reefs’ in tropical, temperate, and polar regions. Constraints on evenness, along with disparity amongst communities in possible functional traits, cast doubt on the utility of global functional diversity comparisons for management of marine systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interspecific synchrony of seabird population growth rate and
breeding success</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2013-ut/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2013-ut/</guid>
      <description>Environmental variability can destabilize communities by causing correlated interspecific fluctuations that weaken the portfolio effect, yet evidence of such a mechanism is rare in natural systems. Here, we ask whether the population dynamics of similar sympatric species of a seabird breeding community are syn- chronized, and if these species have similar exceptional responses to environ- mental variation. We used a 24-year time series of the breeding success and population growth rate of a marine top predator species group to assess the degree of synchrony between species demography.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>