<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on James PW Robinson</title>
    <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on James PW Robinson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental conditions and herbivore biomass determine coral
reef benthic community composition: implications for quantitative
baselines</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2018-tf/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2018-tf/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
Our ability to understand natural constraints on coral reef benthic communities requires quantitative assessment of the relative strengths of abiotic and biotic processes across large spatial scales. Here, we combine underwater images, visual censuses and remote sensing data for 1,566 sites across 34 islands spanning the central- western Pacific Ocean, to empirically assess the relative roles of abiotic and grazing processes in determining the prevalence of calcifying organisms and fleshy algae on coral reefs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Climate Change Research With Open Science</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/tai2018-dd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/tai2018-dd/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
Climate change research aims to understand global environmental change and how it will impact nature and society. The broad scope of climate change impacts means that successful adaptation and mitigation efforts will require an unprecedented collaboration effort that unites diverse disciplines and is able to rapidly respond to evolving climate issues (IPCC, 2014). However, to achieve this aim, climate change research practices need updating: key research findings remain behind journal paywalls, and scientific progress can be impeded by low levels of reproducibility and transparency (Ellison, 2010; Morueta-Holme et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fishing degrades size structure of coral reef fish communities</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2017-xm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2017-xm/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
Fishing pressure on coral reef ecosystems has been frequently linked to reductions of large fishes and reef fish biomass. Associated impacts on overall community structure are, however, less clear. In size-structured aquatic ecosystems, fishing impacts are commonly quantified using size spectra, which describe the distribution of individual body sizes within a community. We examined the size spectra and biomass of coral reef fish communities at 38 US- affiliated Pacific islands that ranged in human presence from near pristine to human population centers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Testing and recommending methods for fitting size spectra to data</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/edwards2017-wp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/edwards2017-wp/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
 The size spectrum of an ecological community characterizes how a property, such as abundance or biomass, varies with body size. Size spectra are often used as ecosystem indicators of marine systems. They have been fitted to data from various sources, including groundfish trawl surveys, visual surveys of fish in kelp forests and coral reefs, sediment samples of benthic invertebrates and satellite remote sensing of chlorophyll.
 Over the past decades, several methods have been used to fit size spectra to data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trophic roles determine coral reef fish community size structure</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2016-wg/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2016-wg/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
Relationships between abundance – body size and trophic position – body size can reveal size structuring in food webs and test ecological theory. Although there is considerable evidence of size structuring in temperate aquatic food webs, little is known about the structure of tropical coral reef food webs. Here, we use underwater visual-census data and nitrogen stable isotope analysis to test if coral reef fish communities (i) are size structured and (ii) follow metabolic scaling rules.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimation of predator-prey mass ratios using stable isotopes:
sources of errors</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/hertz2014-pw/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/hertz2014-pw/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
In aquatic systems, the ratio of pre- dator mass to prey mass (PPMR) is an important constraint on food web structure, and has been correlated with environmental stability. One com- mon approach of estimating PPMR uses nitrogen stable isotopes (δ15N) as an indicator of trophic position, under the assumption that the discrimi- nation between diet and tissue is constant with increasing diet δ15N (an additive approach). How- ever, recent studies have shown that this assump- tion may not be valid and that there is a negative trend between the δ15N of the diet and the dis- crimination value (a scaled approach).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The limitations of diversity metrics in directing global marine
conservation</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2014-ow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2014-ow/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
Biodiversity hotspots have been used extensively in setting conservation priorities for marine ecosystems. A recent Nature publication claims to have uncovered new latitudinal gradients in the evenness of reef communities and new reef hotspots based on functional diversity. Simulation models show that the purported evenness gradient is a mathematical inevitability of differences in species richness and detectability between vastly different marine ecosystems, namely ‘reefs’ in tropical, temperate, and polar regions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interspecific synchrony of seabird population growth rate and
breeding success</title>
      <link>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2013-ut/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jpwrobinson.github.io/publication/robinson2013-ut/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
Environmental variability can destabilize communities by causing correlated interspecific fluctuations that weaken the portfolio effect, yet evidence of such a mechanism is rare in natural systems. Here, we ask whether the population dynamics of similar sympatric species of a seabird breeding community are syn- chronized, and if these species have similar exceptional responses to environ- mental variation. We used a 24-year time series of the breeding success and population growth rate of a marine top predator species group to assess the degree of synchrony between species demography.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>